A Guide to Virginia Business Documents
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #2135
Virginia Business Documents 1793-1898
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
2135
17 volumes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1945 Mar 23
Scope and Content
This collection, 1793-1898, of 17 bound volumes includes ledgers, journals, and day books from businesses in Petersburg and Richmond owned by Thomas Baxter, John Traylor, and Carey Stevens. Francis Follet, Nathan E. Wildman, Steel and Alexander, the Blandford Mill Company, and John Wilder and Joseph Wilder are a few of the businesses and businessmen represented in these account books of mills, contractors, machinery shops, and general stores.
Container List
- Day Book, [general store], Petersburg, 1813-1815; 1) (Box Box 1)
- Journal, [ Petersburg], John Traylor, blacksmith, Carey Stevens; includes Traylor family genealogy on last two pages and an account with Edmund Ruffin, 1813-1826; 2) (Box Box 1)
- Journal, Richmond, Thomas Baxter, 1827-1840; 3) (Box Box 1)
- Ledger, Blandford Mill Company, Petersburg, Thomas Baxter, Francis Follet, Nathan E. Wildman, 1831-1838; 4) (Box Box 1)
- Chequebook, Petersburg, 1845-1854; 5) (Box Box 1)
- Notes and Bills, [ Petersburg], 1851-1855; 6) (Box Box 1)
- Promissory Notebook, [ Petersburg], 1857, n.d.; 7) (Box Box 1)
- Journal, Blandford Mill Company, Petersburg, Thomas Baxter, 1836-1839; 8) (Box Box 2)
- Ledger, [ Blandford Mill Company], Petersburg, Thomas Baxter, 1836-1839, 1847-1854; 9) (Box Box 2)
- Ledger, Petersburg, Thomas Baxter, 1854-1855, 1858-1859; 10) (Box Box 2)
- Journal, [ Tappey Lumsden and Company], Tappey Lumsden; includes many sketches for mill and construction machinery and an order from the Confederate States of America for pike blades, 1862-1864, 1873-1877, 1880-1890; 11) (Box Box 3)
- Journal, Petersburg, 1866-1871; 12) (Box Box 3)
- Day Book, Steel and Alexander, [milling, machinery, and construction company], Petersburg; includes sketches of machinery, 1884-1891 Jan; 13) (Box Box 3)
- Day Book, Steel and Alexander, Petersburg; includes some sketches of machinery, 1891 Feb-1898; 14) (Box Box 3)
- Ledger, [general store], [ John and Joseph Wilder], Petersburg; includes accounts for tobacco, wheat, corn; accounts for the ship Rebecca, schooner Nancy; some accounts for women, 1793-1803; 15) (Box Oversize)
- Ledger, [general store], [ Buchanan V. Pollek], Petersburg; includes many plantation accounts, especially for "Plantation at Archers Hill"; accounts for the sloops Dispatch and Lively, for the schooner Martha Ann; names and occupations listed together; many "Negro Account" listings and accounts for women, 1806-1820; 16) (Box Oversize)
- Journal, [ Steel and Alexander], [ Petersburg]; includes papers from 1862 re: "Table for Cutting Gear Blanks", 1890-1893; 17) (Box Oversize)